or something I don't know that's not how
our stops work I don't know that is not
how uh the shutter speed yeah 30 so I
can tell you a story that you can use to
blackmail me yeah I know okay
so when I was an undergraduate I I was
working very lucky to be working with a
very famous evolutionary biologist named
Bob Traverse we just accidentally ended
up at the University of California Santa
Cruz where he happened to be and I was
already really deeply interested in
evolution and so anyway took his of
course I'm Heather and I became friends
with him he took me to Jamaica to be his
research assistant and I was doing
photographic work I'm he was studying
lizards and he was studying a hypothesis
called the Hamilton Zook hypothesis that
says that the displays that males have
that females require them to show in
order to to mate with them that these
displays actually are evidence of being
free of pathogens that that's what
they're what that's what males are
advertising is that they have been
resistant to pathogens and that their
resistance would be something that they
could pass on to offspring so females
would be very interested in it so anyway
we were looking at dewlaps which are
these little flaps that these lizards
extend below their necks that are often
colorful and in most species and I was
doing the photographic work capturing
the images of the dewlap so that they
could be compared and Bob who loves
Jamaica Merida Jamaican woman they were
divorced at the point that I was working
with Bob but nonetheless ia's ensconced
himself in Jamaican culture as much as
possible and loves a good joint as much
or more than the next guy was constantly
smoking pot while he was working which
is not abnormal in a Jamaican working
environment the pot isn't so
strong that it gets in the way if you're
working so people smoke bother them they
do work and you know no big deal but he
kept offering it to me and I had to lay
down the law with him no pot until we
were done working for the morning
because I couldn't keep track of the
damn f-stops since it's a reciprocal so
anyway if the f-stops were done in some
other way where they weren't a
mathematical reciprocal maybe I could
have smoked pot you know men tend to be
like use humor like human males use
humor yes as a display yes is that
somehow a display of the pathogen-free
mind no no I really don't think so but
yeah so the thing is this whole
hypothesis that sexual displays are an
indicator of being pathogen-free
has always struck me as not quite
complete enough in other words a female
doesn't particularly care whether you're
pathogen-free because your immune system
is highly functional if your eyesight
sucks what he cares is that she gets a
genome in which everything pretty well
works and so my guess would be that the
hypothesis is wrong then it includes
cases in which a vulnerability to
pathogens is something that the female
wants to avoid but really if she wants
to avoid anything that will get in the
way of the well-being of her offspring
and so she's looking for an integrative
measure that says effectively how
successful are you in the habitat so
that does raise the question of why
males are so often funny and why females
are so attuned to humor and I will say I
think this is changing in human beings
in recent years that there has there's a
long tradition of female comics but the
degree to which women in our society are
consciously funny rather than just
consciously observers of humor has
changed a lot I think in my lifetime but
I find it particularly telling that
women actually rate humor very highly
when they are discussing traits in
potential mates the thing that makes for
really high-quality humor is the the
noticing of stuff that others are aware
of but wouldn't think to put words to so
if you think about you know Jerry
Seinfeld or some other well-known comic
the surfacing of certain truths that are
easily recognized but that you've never
heard said before is very very funny and
so my guess would be that for young men
in a traditional environment where
success or failure functions according
to whatever men have successful that
have succeeded at or failed at that the
the ability to notice that which others
can recognize once it said but wouldn't
think to have said out loud is an
indicator really of a kind of ability to
spot opportunity also there's something
very interesting in the fact that I mean
if you've ever watched some hierarchical
organization where there's some person
often a guy at the very top of the
organization you know the CEO of the
company and they can tell really lousy
jokes just low-quality jokes from the
point of view of timing or anything but
it causes a lot of laughter so to an
extent in a classic environment a female
who was noticing that a man was causing
others to laugh would be able to detect
two things one either that man is able
to notice things that others aren't as
capable of noticing and that that would
be potentially a good bet for somebody
who would find an opportunity in a
marketplace or in a habitat or whatever
some opportunity to others had missed or
that a man has the kind of power that
causes others to laugh at their jokes in
order
to ingratiate themselves and either one
is good from the point of view of
picking a mate who is liable to be in a
position to provide well for a family
and protect them things like that in
entertain you along the way and
entertain you along the way yeah so you
have that classic thing that I mean I
don't know if women really did say it
very much but you know he makes me laugh
that that's a really strong positive
sign would be yeah exactly well so you
said that that one one formulation of
humor is the putting together of things
in a way we're making an observation in
a way that other people's haven't seen
so there's a novelty aspect but that's
humor but isn't wisdom a version of
viewing that as wisdom related to this
foolishness well let's talk a little bit
about about way stuff so the first thing
to realize is that wisdom has a
relationship to intelligence but it's
not a straightforward linear
relationship that it is perfectly
possible for a person to be extremely
smart and very unwise and that in
recognizing you know in taking that
smart person who is unwise and basically
subtracting the wisdom from the
intelligence we can figure out what it
actually contains that's special and
what I would argue is that there are
lots of things that are just simply true
that one can notice or calculate but
that there are also lots of effects that
you know exist a couple of levels up
that cause the simple calculation to be
misleading with respect to ultimately
what is valuable so there's a way in
which a wise person knows not only how
to calculate what's true but knows how
to wait a bunch of truths relative to
each other in order to figure out what
the best pathway through something might
be so it's it's basically an integrative
function rather than a raw mental
horsepower function one thing I find
myself noticing as a parent and as a
professor of many students is that one
of the things about youth that tends to
get in the way of children or college
students is that they don't they're
impatient about certain things that are
very important not to be impatient about
and so for example if you are interested
in solving deep analytical puzzles right
if that's your taste you want to know
you know why why males in some species
display these elaborate flashy dances or
plumage or whatever that's a difficult
question and if you have to know the
answer right now well then you're not
going to make it because the fact is
nobody who studied the question has
gotten there yet
so you're gonna have to do something
better than all of those very smart
people who have attempted and largely
failed to this point to fully answer the
question we know some something about
the answer but we don't know it fully
and so what are you gonna do differently
well one thing you might do differently
is file the question in a place that as
information that's relevant to the
answer passes in front of you in one way
or another you collect it and you build
a model and you begin to test hypotheses
rather than feeling like oh my god we've
been lecturing about sexual selection
for two and a half hours now just tell
us
what
why are these animals doing this crazy
stuff so I guess what I would what I
would say is that I'm not sure I would
say it is the core of wisdom but I would
certainly say it is a core of wisdom
delayed gratification delayed
gratification is one of the central
pieces of wisdom the ability to invest
in something in the present in a way
that it may be costly while knowing that
what you're pursuing is some benefit
that may be substantially down the road
and if you think about the difference
between the way the way highly
successful adults and very smart kids
behave you'll realize that the very
smart kid is very eager to demonstrate
exactly what they've got and the wise
adult may be willing to you know be
working on something that isn't
obviously a value for most of the period
of time that they're working on it in an
effort to six months or a year or maybe
even five years down the road have
something that's worth all of that
investment to show for the project so
the ability to to understand that you
are investing at a cost now for a
benefit that will only emerge much later
is
it's maybe the most important lesson
that takes a smart person allows them to
become wise and that's a lesson that
takes time to learn well that's a good
question is how how does an impatient
young person ever discover this because
that impatience will cause them never to
happen on to to a situation in which
this style of looking at things pays off
so in some sense one of the tragedies of
wisdom is that it isn't automatic that
you accumulate it simply if you live
enough years you tend to get wiser but
you don't necessarily get what we you
know we don't say most most people
aren't wise most people are too easily
trapped by the false promise of a
get-rich-quick scheme or some idea that
seems incredibly promising but doesn't
pan out whereas something like you know
an inventor may build dozens of
prototypes each one of which will suck
up resources and time and none of them
will save enough labor or provide enough
extra value to justify what was put into
it but that isn't their purpose their
purpose is to discover what you didn't
know about the process of building the
object in order to get it to work really
well so one way to say it might be that
the the product of prototypes is the
improved mental model rather than the
object itself and in fact this is one of
the things I always wonder why nobody
says this to college students but
college students produce a lot of stuff
during college those of us who have
graduated from college realize that very
few things that we produced in college
are ever published or seen by anybody
they don't matter and that isn't their
purpose the purpose is in learning to
produce them your mind is enhanced such
that later on when you decide what it is
that needs to be produced in the world
or what it is that you want to
contribute you'd have the tools to go
about doing it and so I often fear that
because the work that takes place in
school looks a lot like the work that
takes place in a job that students think
that their purpose in school is the
production of stuff in production of
papers or something rather than the
production of an enhanced mind that's
capable of being pointed at very
different problems later it's not the
production of value but the production
of the capacity to create value that's
well sent the production of tools sharp
enough to do something refined later on
and hands adroit enough to wield those
right so how do you how do you teach
wisdom well there then failure oddly you
know first of all there are a lot of
ways to teach successfully and one of
the un-- one of the foolish things about
our educational system is that it tends
to shunt us all into some idealized
model of how to convey things like
wisdom and because it's such a poor
match for most of us we're not very
effective at it so discovering that the
way you teach wisdom may be very
different from the way somebody else
teaches wisdom and that that is not an
indictment of either method is one kind
of wisdom but I would say for me the
recognition that far too much of what we
understand is generated by or is passed
to us by people who are conveying
something on some authority and I'm not
indicted it by saying it's authority it
may be that a chemist is telling you how
a reaction works based on long years of
exposure to chemistry but from the point
of view of the person who's listening to
that lecture this isn't something that
you've established yourself this is
something that you're taking on the
authority of the chemist who who told
you that and so the problem is with
chemistry
you can be pretty sure that if somebody
who spent their career studying these
processes is telling you XY and z are
true they probably are on the other hand
there are a lot of things over you know
in the humanities the social sciences
even biology which is so complicated
that we don't have a complete model of
it it is very easy to be lured into
believing things that sound like they're
right and the authorities believe are
right that are actually false so there's
no shortage of such such things that you
know have compelled people and mislead
them deeply like the idea that you know
depression is in general the result of a
chemical imbalance right or that
addiction results because of a cycle in
which your body simply comes to be
dependent on the molecule that you've
introduced and when you take that
molecule away you suffer from a deficit
of it it's not that there's no truth in
either of these there are cases of
depression being the result of the
chemical imbalance but depression is
also likely to result from circumstances
that are very difficult to navigate
especially developmental circumstances
can build counterproductive patterns and
addiction we now know is in large
measure the result of not having good
options that whether we're talking about
animal models or people that people who
have rewarding stuff to choose are much
less likely to become addicted and that
people become addicted to various things
like opiates when they're stuck so
getting people unstuck is sort of the
key my point my point is that both of
these models lasted for decades where
people passed them on as if they were
true and in fact they were at the very
least much less than a complete
explanation of any
so the result of all this is that one
should become suspicious of any truth
that is heavily dependent on the
accuracy of some authorities
understanding of something that is
complex enough that the authority could
actually be wrong and you would have no
way of knowing and a cure for that the
answer to your question about how you
teach people to be wise is you induce
them to confront some system in which
authority plays little or no role so for
example if you let's say you take up
robotics and what you're gonna do is
you're gonna build little robots that do
funny things and aren't especially
useful to anybody nonetheless if you're
gonna build a robot and you're going to
get it to accomplish something
well you can't fool the robot into
function either you've put the parts
together in a way that is logical that
is capable of lifting the loads that
you're intending it to lift or you'll
miss calculated in it it won't lift
those loads or it won't behave in a
coordinated fashion and so the the key
is that any system in which you will
know at the point that you have actually
come to understand the system because
the object itself will work or in a
different case knowing a natural system
well enough that you can predict things
you don't know about where to find a
creature or how that creature is likely
to behave and responds to some stimulus
or something those systems are ones in
which you are incapable of deluding
yourself into believing attractive
fictions because if what you believe is
false it won't be effective so I am a
strong advocate for the idea of taking
authority out of the role of training
your mind to function well to the extent
possible there is a relationship between
Authority and wisdom like the wise man
or at least within the
and cultural sphere those who are wise
tend to be given a certain amount of
authority or they're speaking from a
position of authority
absolutely but did they earn that
authority perhaps or well you know
they're certainly false
there's false wisdom you know there's
self-help gurus that aren't in fact very
insightful on the other hand what you
will tend to discover if you look at
what people who are actually understood
to be wise tend to say is it it often
has a counterintuitive kind of ring to
it right
and so that counterintuitive Ness is
about it's really a product of not
leaping to conclusions the intuitive
conclusion seems right and you can
convince yourself that it's true the
wise conclusion requires you to step
back and to think more carefully about
in what way something might be incorrect
so let me give you a cool example this
is from the book Thinking Fast and Slow
by Daniel Kahneman he points out and
actually he takes the example from a
stint that he did in the Israeli
military in which he was charged with
trying to improve the training protocol
for fighter pilots and the the trainers
were under the impression that rewarding
people didn't work and that punishing
them did work and the reason that they
thought this was because it was more or
less reflected in their experience that
when somebody did something really well
and you congratulated them for it the
next time they went up and did something
they tended to do it less well and when
somebody did something really badly and
you scolded them for it they tended to
improve alright and that seems like a
very straightforward pattern well if
that's true if you scold people and they
do better
you're congratulating when they do worse
than obviously what you should do is
sculpt them right well no it's actually
not true
the pattern is the result of something
called reversion to the mean reversion
to the mean means that when you do
something better than you usually do it
chances are the next time you try you
won't do as well right if you're
throwing darts and you tend to throw
them at some distance from the center
and you happen to get one really close
to the center chances you're gonna pull
it off twice in a row are pretty low so
if you imagine person throws a dart it
gets way closer to the center than they
tend again you say that was great and
then they throw another dart and it's
not anywhere near close to the center
you'll get the sense that they didn't
react well to being congratulated when
in fact it was just a reversion to the
mean and that explains the other pattern
too which is somebody does something
really crappy compared to their usual
and you say how could you possibly have
screwed that up and then the next time
they tend to do better that's not an
indication that you're scolding them did
them any good so in any case it's it
takes wisdom to ignore the fact that the
pattern seems to reflect this very
obvious way of organizing rewards and
penalties to get people to succeed and
notices that there's some entirely other
reason for the pattern that you think
you've observed the cleverest scientists
in my field at least and my guess is
this would be true in every field but in
my field the cleverest scientists are
the ones that have really good intuition
right we tend to think they're the ones
with the the fastest highest horsepower
brains and just don't think this is
right they're the ones that know how to
allocate their attention in order to
spot the things that others haven't seen
or the ones that know the sound of a an
appealing fiction if you can if you know
what an appealing fiction sounds like
there's a pretty good chance that those
appealing fictions may have become the
assumptions that support some wrong
model and if you're trying to replace
that model with one that works better
than just knowing that something doesn't
quite
ring true that it's the kind of thing
people will have embraced because they
want it to be true rather than because
they actually have that that knowledge
that gives you a way into puzzles or
another way of thinking about this let's
suppose that you're interested in
solving big questions in a field where
there still are lots of big questions
like my field for example well what are
the chances that you are going to be
smarter in the sense of having a higher
horsepower brain than all of the other
people who've looked at those same
questions
vanishing below right there are a lot of
smart people they pass through all of
these fields so what are the chances
that you're going to be better read than
all of the people who have looked at
these questions again vanishingly well
there will be people who've read
everything so you need to do something
else
that distinguishes you in some way in
fact you have to overcome the advantage
of the really well read extremely high
horsepower brains that have tried to
traverse that territory ahead of you and
it involves counterintuitive things like
scrutinizing the observations that they
all accepted without question right if
you go back and look at the observation
or the the the assumptions of the models
that they're using whereas everybody
else's instinct is to go forward and
just simply accept the the observations
and pursue you know things at the remote
edge well should one of those
assumptions be wrong then that's where
your advantage comes from so this
results in a kind of it results in a
kind of wisdom and weirdly wisdom has a
kind of slow almost childlike character
to it
isn't that a contradiction
um yeah why is it a contradiction it's a
good question I would say Bob Traverse
pointed out in this paper that I think I
talked to you about once before where he
advised people not to take a job any at
any institution that didn't have
undergraduates his point about
undergraduates is they don't yet know
what questions they're not supposed to
ask and so they they keep you agile
because stuff that you've long ago given
up on thinking about they'll cause you
to return to it and if there's something
wrong with it you'll discover it that
way so I guess the point would be if you
took all of the questions that people
don't ask once they've left the early
stages of some field some tiny fraction
of those questions are still good and in
fact really good all right they're
really the thing you should be thinking
about
but you've moved on from the whole
category well okay now you're gonna be
stuck competing with everybody else
using the same tools they are and you're
unlikely to succeed so when I say that
the wisdom seems childlike wisdom is
like the edit of all of the vast swath
of undisciplined questions that children
asked to that small number of
undisciplined questions that are good
enough to point the direction that
everybody's been missing you were
talking about that which is
counterintuitive
is kind of has a relationship with the
wisdom and you also said that good
scientists need to have a certain sort
of intuition or to be intuitive so it's
almost like a wisdom is a form of
counterintuitive intuition or an
intuition for that which is
counterintuitive
I think because wisdom is often phrased
counter-intuitively
maybe more poetically than other kinds
of truth it liberates one to search in a
way that is nonlinear which is
oftentimes what you need to do in order
to find that thing that is missing you
need to search in some way that you may
not be able to fully justify and that it
is it is Liberty
to search you know in a way that cannot
be fully accounted for but nonetheless
often results in progress
you still need to maintain your
direction and your smarts and your
intelligence once you veer out of the
authority of that standard truth or the
accepted narrative you're letting go of
something you're entering into a danger
zone you're entering into the unknown
but you need to somehow keep your smarts
about you when you go there you still
need to have some sort of guiding
principle or guiding feeling or guiding
intuition so that it's not completely
wasted so that you don't become just as
confused as that confusion that you're
trying to confront well Luca Turin has a
thing that he says in his book the
emperor is actually not his book the
Emperor of Sampath the book is about him
what he said is that great scientists
have to be I think he says bipolar and I
think III I don't agree with him in the
literal sense I don't think bipolar is
exactly what he means but his argument
is that in order to do something really
new you have to be able to be passionate
about the search for some new answer
enough that you can follow follow that
passion you can fall in love with the
idea enough to pursue it and get it
right and then you have to turn around
and attempt to tear it down in order to
figure out if it's actually correct and
so there's something about the the
tendency to
just to seek an answer with what might
seem like
unjustified levels of obsession and then
to take that same answer that you've
worked so hard to try to find and to
attempt to dismantle it so forcefully
that if it resists you know actually
it's right there's almost I feel like
almost a loneliness inherent in that
like an ever a restlessness never being
able to just relax and say this is the
truth Eureka I found it well that is uh
that is a funny aspect of the way how do
I say this
at some point as as I was going through
training to be a scientist like
everybody else I looked at what the
future might hold what does it take to
get a job in which somebody actually
pays you to pursue scientific truths and
what are those jobs and what truth can
you pursue and whether it was completely
conscious or not it became pretty clear
that a the chances of getting such a job
were pretty darn small and if you did
get such a job the questions that you
would end up pursuing would be generally
pretty narrow they'd be in some little
field where you've got to be the expert
or one of a couple of experts but it
wasn't going to be the beautiful search
for marvelous truths that make you smile
day after day and I think in light of
that that discovery which you know
happens in graduate school I started
doing something else which was I mean
maybe I didn't realize how dangerous it
was to building a career but I started
pursuing answers to questions that that
it seemed like we should know but that
we didn't right so I start that I didn't
think of it immediately this way but it
sort of started to be like big-game
hunting like there were things in
Ellucian area biology which were big
they were unanswered and nobody really
knew which direction to go and so sort
of seemed like they were intractable in
my feeling was okay why are they
intractable and what would it take to
make them tractable and the I think I
developed a toolkit for figuring out how
to approach those puzzles with enough
naivete that I didn't make the same
mistakes as the people for whom they
were intractable and that became a
tremendous amount of fun but in answer
to your question you get to what you
accept yourself is the right answer to
some very big puzzle and there is that
you know the famous Eureka moment there
is a minute it's really it's almost a
it's a giddy childish feeling but it's
really it's marvelous but it does make
you hungry for the next one right and so
there's a way in which it's not like I I
think I found the answer to this great
puzzle and now I can take it easy it's
like nowhere do I get more of that
you